你好
I'm Yu Takahashi from Japan.
Today I'll talk about macros
in SwiftUI Preview.
Let's start with what I wanted to build.
I usually use SwiftData
for my indie apps,
but when we use Previews for SwiftData,
we need to add a model container
and more, like this.
And manually insert mock data.
But I wanted to simplify this
with my custom macro,
like this PreviewContent macro.
This macro generates a new struct
that takes mock values as parameters.
It looks very nice, right?
However, I faced an error.
Compiler can't find the struct
that the macro generates.
It seems like a bug.
But what if I write the struct manually?
Of course, the error is gone.
Now it can be previewed.
So I looked into it.
It turns out I'm not the only one.
There's a thread on the Swift forums
reporting the exact same symptom.
The access method generated by
the Observable macro
cannot be found in the Preview macro.
I'll come back to this later.
Before going deeper,
let me describe Swift macros.
There are two types of macros.
freestanding macros and attached macros.
Also, there are many types
of attached macros,
like peer, member, and more.
The main characters in this topic
are the freestanding macro
and the peer-attached macro.
My custom PreviewContent macro
is a peer-attached macro,
and it creates a new struct.
SwiftUI's Preview macro
is a freestanding macro.
And the reference to the generated struct
is inside its argument.
Here's the problem.
According to the proposal, macros
are expanded in two separate phases.
First, the compiler type-checks
the macro's arguments
without expanding the macro.
Second, the compiler expands the macro
and type-checks the result.
The body of the Preview macro
is type-checked in the first phase.
However, the generated struct is expanded
and type-checked in the second phase.
And now the reason is clear, right?
When the compiler type-checks
the Preview macro's arguments,
the generated struct isn't there yet.
Let's go back to the forum example.
Both the foo() and access() methods
come from the Observable macro.
But only foo() resolves. Why?
The foo() method is part
of the Observable protocol.
As we can see at the top,
the attached Observable macro
declares conformance
to the Observable protocol.
So the model class conforms
This is obvious
without expanding the macro.
So the Observable protocol,
including the foo() method,
is visible in the Preview macro.
However, the access() method is different.
access() is a member which
the Observable macro generates
inside the model class,
after macro expansion.
This is exactly the kind of problem
I just said earlier.
So, is this a bug?
No, this is the design.
The proposal clearly says:
keep macro-generated names
invisible in other macros' arguments.
However, this behavior isn't mentioned
in any of the documents shown.
There are issues
if names can be visible on other macros:
self-validation of arguments,
order dependency,
which Swift doesn't prefer,
and expansion cost.
The alternative way to preview
using my custom PreviewContent macro
is to use the old PreviewProvider struct.
Because this is just a plain struct,
it'll be type-checked
at the same time as
the attached macro expansion.
Using the old API feels wrong,
but today this is the only answer.
Thank you.